# Slim Ouertani June-81, Tunisian

ouertani@gmail.com • (00966)-(0)-583012381 • Riyadh (Saudi Arabia) linkedin.com/in/ouertani • ouertani.github.io • jroller.com/ouertani • twitter.com/ouertani

## Architect, InfoQ Fr Editor

## Big Data Science, Cloud & SOA Certified Trainer Togaf, Archimate, PMP, Spring, Java, Cmmi, ITIL, Mongo, Scala

## Summary

Slim Ouertani is solution architect, InfoQ-Fr editor, Big Data Science, Cloud and SOA Certified trainer , founder and organizer of Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup. After his engineer's degree in computer science, Slim spent over than 10 years in multinational companies such as Orange, Sagem and STMicroelectronics as architect, international agile coach and Head of IT development department. His main role was to build, design and collaborate in the development of enterprise solutions.

Slim regularly contributes to InfoQ-FR community where he is the author of many articles and news. you to follow him on twitter @ouertani.

He's broad certified as in addition to his SOA, Cloud and Big Data Science certifications: Trainer, Architect & Engineer, Slim holds multiple certifications including Togaf 9, Archimate 2, PMP, ITIL, CMMi, Mongo, Spring, JAVA, SCALA and reactive programming...

Trained as an architect, Slim specializes in enterprise Java development, functional programming focusing on highly scalable applications and now expanding his experience to cloud computing.

Slim enjoys open source contribution and invite

## Experience

## Al-Elm Information Security

#### **Solution Architect**

RIYADH, SAUDI ARABIA 06-2014 - present

- Member/Founder of ELM Development Architecture Center of Excellence.
- EPG committee member, responsible of the architecture models, oversee the process architecture, approve it and ensuring the process improvement.
- Architecting and Designing enterprise solutions using diverse technology stack
- Work with peers to conduct Solution Architecture Reviews for a broad set of projects
- Review and provide input into functional & non-functional requirements
- Provide consulting and conduct reviews through the development lifecycle
- Defining the Architecture and guiding the use of various tools, technologies and techniques in the realization of that Architecture
- Create and maintain a set of standard practices, patterns and anti-patterns and ensure the appropriate usage of that.

## Sofrecom (Orange FT Group)

Tunis, Tunisia 03-2013 - 06-2014

## Software Architect, International Agile Coach Manage and direct virtual distributed teams

- Make or Buy Analysis
- Establish regular meetings to review technical designs and provide mentoring and guidance
- Mentor development teams on different architecture and design paradigms or practices
- Maintain a knowledge base of emerging technologies and products
- Scrum Master, Enterprise Architect, Apache Camel, Spring
  CXF, Spring Batch, Atomikos, ActiveMq, Jonas, hibernate

### Zenika

**JEE Architect** 

Paris, FRANCE

12-2012 - 03-2013

## • Client: Bouygues Telecom

- Project: Home Automation (2 months)
- BBox embedded automation solution communicating with centralized system

  - Embedded: OSGI, REST server/client, Raspberry pi- Server: Fuse ESB, CXF, Camel, Spring, Jax-Rs, Osgi, Maven
- Client: SwissPost
- Project: Image Plus (2 months)
- Online outsourcing solution for picture processing.
  - Scrum, Kanban, Jenkies, Git, Cloudbees, Maven
  - MVP, Spring 3.1, GWT 2.5, JPA 2

#### Orange

Tunis, Tunisia 01-2010 - 11-2012

• JEE 6, MDB, JPA, Scala, Wicket, Play, J2ME, Spring ROO, WS, Glassfish, Talend, Birt

• Development and implementation of a web service platform :

- JEE 6, SCALA, EJB 3.1, JAX-WS, Oracle, JPA
   IN/AIR, BSCS/CMS/Data Charging/CRM/IVR/USSD
   Development of the "after sales service" solution: Play 1.2.x, groovy, jquery
- Launch of BI project: Talend, Birt, Oracle Bulk SMS: Wicket, JEE 6, JPA, Postgres Unbarring SMS: J2ME, JAX-WS, MDB, JPA

**Head of Development and Tools Manager** 

- Different applications: inter systems and synchronization platforms, web application...

#### Sagem Software & Technologies

Tunis, Tunisia

**Solution Architect** 

06-2009 - 01-2010

• Architecture design and integration of a communication server and administration of remote

JEE, JMS, Spring, GWT, AndroMda, Hibernate, SMSJboss, ActiveMq, MDA

**Solution Architect** 03-2008 - 06-2009

 Modular OSGi Server architecture under Linux platform responsible for controlling and interacting with electricity counters in order to retrieve statistics and have data storing/manipulation via different technologies and frameworks

 OSGI, SCA, Spring DM, JAX-WS, JPA, GPRS, GSM/DATA, SMS, SNMP4j, Hessian, Ftp, Equinox, IETTY, POSTGRESOL

DISTRIBUTED COMPUTING, Cryptography

#### **Solution Architect & Team Leader**

12-2007 - 03-2008

 Designing an SOA architecture and implementation of an Intranet service for human resources using liferay portal.

JEE5, EJB3, JAX-WS, JSF, PORTLET, JPA, SOA

- JEE5, EJB3, JAX-W5, J5F, FORTLET, J173, 502. - GLASSFISH V2, TOMCAT6, LIFERAY 4.4, POSTGRESQL

**STMicroelectronics** Tunis, Tunisia

Coordinator 02-2006 - 12-2007

 Implementing Intranet tools used for monitoring the evolution of validation campaigns. J2EE, JSF, Hibernate/JPA, JAXB/JAXP, Design Pattern

TOMCAT 5.5, POSTGRESQL

12-2005 - 02-2006

• Validating processors and compilers under different platforms.

- Linux, Solaris, Cygwin, Mingwin, Perl, Shell

**GL TRADE** Tunis, Tunisia

#### Developer & designer

08-2005 - 12-2005

• GL TACTICS: A trader module enhancing the efficiency of the negotiating teams giving them the possibility to customize the implementation strategies and accelerate the decision process.

- C++, Design Pattern

Please refer to my Linked-in profile for a more complete list of work experiences along with recommendations.

#### Certificate

Big Data Science Trainer, Arcitura 09-2016 Big Data Science Engineer, Arcitura With Honors, 08-2016 Big Data Professional, Arcitura WITH HONORS, 05-2016 Archimate Certified, Open Group Score 82%, 02-2016 Archimate Foundation, Open Group Score 97%, 02-2016 Cloud Trainer, Arcitura 10-2015 Cloud Architect, Arcitura WITH HONORS, 10-2015 Cloud Professional, Arcitura WITH HONORS, 09-2015 Togaf Certified, Open Group Score 90%, 06-2015 ITIL Foundation, Exin Score 95%, 06-2015 Togaf Foundation, Open Group Score 95%, 04-2015

Project Management Professional, PMI	03-2015	
SOA Trainer, Arcitura	01-2015	
SOA Architect, Arcitura	With Honors, 12-2014	
SOA Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 11-2014	
Introduction to Cmmi for development, Cmmi Institute	09-2014	
Entrepreneurship for all, EFFECTUATION, EMLYON	Score 75,8%, 01-2014	
Principles of Reactive Programming, Coursera	Score 97.5%, 01-2014	
MongoDB for DBAs, MongoDB	Score 94%, 11-2013	
MongoDb for java, MongoDb	Score 95%, 10-2013	
Spring Framework 3, Pivotal	Score 94%, 02-2013	
Java 6 Programmer Certified Professional, Oracle	Score 100%, 08-2012	
Team Performance, STMicroelectronics	04-2007	
English, British Council	4B, 02-2007	
GL Certified Professional, GL TRADE	09-2005	

### Education

National School of Computer ScienceENSI  Graduation Project in Computer Engineering	Tunis,Tunisia 2005
National School of Computer Science ENSI Engineer Degree in Computer Science	Tunis, Tunisia 2002 – 2005
Tunis Preparatory Institute for Engineering StudiesIPEIT Preparatory Courses (Math Sup, Math Spe)	Tunis, Tunisia 2000 – 2002
Hannibal (Pre-university Secondary Education)	Ariana, Tunisia 1994 – 2000

#### **Other Activities**

## InfoQ Fr Editor

http://www.infoq.com/fr/author/Slim-Ouertani

## Founder & Organizer

Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup

http://www.meetup.com/Riyadh-IT-Architecture

#### **BLOGGGING**

http://java.dzone.com/users/slim.ouertani

http://ouertani.github.io

http://www.jroller.com/ouertani

http://twitter.com/ouertani

### **MAGAZINE**

From Microservices to SOA - 20.07.2015 Service Technology Magazine - Issue XCI http://servicetechmag.com/I91/0715-1

#### **INTERVIEW**

Paremus, SCA with OSGI, David Savage

http://www.prosyst.com/

07.02.2009

http://goo.gl/H5yJzY

### **STAMPLE**

https://stample.co Scala, Akka, Play

ElasticSearch, MongoDb, Amazon S3, GreenCloud

## **OPEN SOURCE**

https://github.com/ouertani http://www.reactive-streams.org

#### v. 4

# Computer Skills

Build tools Version contro	Functional programming, EA, UML, Design Pattern, MVC, MDA, OO, MVP Microservices, Reactive, N-tiers, SOA, SCA, Actor CloudBees, Heroku, App Engine, Amazon S3, GreenCloud Scrum, Kanban Metro, JAX-WS,CXF,JAX-RS,Hessian, Rest, Axis SCALA, Java/JEE/OSGI, C/C++/C#, ADA, COBOL, PLAY, GWT, Vert.x, WICKET, JSF, PORTLET, JSP, SERVLET, APPLET, HTML XML, XSL,XSD, JAXP, JAXB, Stax, SAX, DOM, SCALA XML PostgresSQL, MySQL, Oracle, MongoDb JPA, Hibernate, Toplink, EclipseLink, Slick Glassfish V3, Tomcat 5/6/7, Equinox, JBOSS AS, Jonas 4, OC4J Spring, Spring DM, Liferay 4.4, Fuse ESB, Camel, Spring Batch, ElasticSearch UNIX/LINUX, Mac OS, Windows XP, Windows NT, SOLARIS Netbeans, Eclipse, Idea, JDeveloper 10g IceScrum, Bugzilla, Trello Gradle, Maven, Sbt, Javac, Scalac, Ant oliGit, Subversion, Perforce, CVS, Jazz Trello, Slack, Github, Codex, Wiki, Sharepoint	
Training	<u>-</u>	
U	anagement Professional, PMP	11.2014
•	ign pattern: White board & Extender	08.2009
•	im Ôuertani	
	itecture with Newton	01.2009
-	avid Savage & Mike Francis hitecture and environment	05.2008
	oman Roelofsen	05.2000
Publication	ic.	
	n: for-comprehension à la sauce Java 8	22.07.2015
	Faux Jumeaux ?	23.07.2015 25.11.2014
	tion Java: methods & fonctions	29.07.2014
•	es en Java ?	30.06.2014
	dans le compilateur Java	02.06.2014
	ppoline avec Java 8	18.04.2014
	er les iteratees avec Java	01.11.2013
Le Trio: Akka, Spring et Scala		16.10.2013
Rest with Scala and Vert.x		18.02.2013
Fun with Scala and Vert.x		11.02.2013
Getting S	tarted with Play 2.1 , Scala 2.10 and Slick 0.11.1	01.11.2012
	Please refer to my Linked-in profile for a more complete list of publications since 2008.	
News		
Publication	on de la Nouvelle Spécification d'ArchiMate 3.0	22.06.2016
Java EE et les Anges Gardiens		11.05.2016
Microservice antipatterns à Qcon London 2016		14.04.2016
MongoDB: la magie des Reactive-Streams avec les Capped Collections		21.05.2015
Publication de l'API Reactive Streams 1.0		07.05.2015
Docker, le	dernier clou dans le cercueil des serveurs d'applications Java ?	19.03.2015

## Languages